The Longest Day is a war, action, drama film directed by Ken Annakin.
The retelling of June 6, 1944, from the perspectives of the
Germans, US, British, Canadians, and the Free French.
Marshall Erwin Rommel, touring the defenses being established as part of the Reich's Atlantic Wall, notes
to his officers that when the Allied invasion comes they must be stopped on the beach.
"For the Allies as well as the Germans, it will be the longest day"
Lt. Col. Benjamin Vandervoort, played by John Wayne.
Brig. Gen. Norman Cota, played by Robert Mitchum.
Brig. Gen. Theodore Roosevelt Jr., played by Henry Fonda.
Flying Officer David Campbell, played by Richard Burton.
Pvt. Flanagan, played by Sean Connery.
RAF Officer Mac, played by Leslie Phillips.
The Longest Day is a 1962 American epic war film based on Cornelius Ryan's 1959 non-fiction
book of the same name about the D-Day landings in Normandy on June 6, 1944.
The film was produced by Darryl F.
Zanuck for 20th Century-Fox, and is directed by Ken Annakin (British and French
exteriors), Andrew Marton (American exteriors), and Bernhard Wicki (German scenes).
The screenplay was written by Ryan, with additional material written by
Romain Gary, James Jones, David Pursall and Jack Seddon.
The film features a large international ensemble cast that includes John Wayne, Kenneth More, Richard Todd, Robert Mitchum, Richard Burton, Steve Forrest, Sean Connery, Henry Fonda, Red Buttons, Peter
Lawford, Eddie Albert, Jeffrey Hunter, Stuart Whitman, Tom Tryon, Rod Steiger, Leo Genn, Gert Fröbe, Irina Demick, Bourvil, Curd Jürgens, George Segal, Robert Wagner, Paul Anka and Arletty.
Many of these actors played roles that were essentially cameo appearances.
Several cast members had seen action as servicemen during the war, including Albert, Fonda, Genn, More, Steiger and Todd, the latter having
been among the first British officers to land in Normandy in Operation Overlord and participate in the assault on Pegasus Bridge.
The filmmakers employed several actual Allied and Axis D-Day participants as
consultants, many of whom had their roles re-enacted in the film.
These included Günther Blumentritt (a former German general), James M.
Gavin (an American general), Frederick Morgan (Deputy Chief of Staff at SHAEF), John Howard (who led the airborne assault on the Pegasus Bridge), Lord Lovat (who commanded the 1st Special Service Brigade), Philippe Kieffer (who led his men in the assault on Ouistreham), Marie-Pierre Kœnig (who commanded the Free French
Forces in the invasion), Max Pemsel (a German general), Werner Pluskat (the major who was the first German officer to see the invasion fleet), Josef "Pips" Priller (the hot-headed pilot who was one of the few Luftwaffe pilots to strafe the beaches) and Lucie Rommel (widow of Field Marshal Erwin Rommel).
The Longest Day premiered in France on September 25,
1962, and in the United States on October 4.
It received acclaim from critics and was a significant commercial success,
becoming the highest-grossing black-and-white movie at the time.
At the 35th Academy Awards, the film was nominated for five Oscars, including Best Picture, and
won awards for Best Cinematography (Black-and-White) and Best Special Effects.
The film explores themes of steel helmet, resistance,
allies, world war ii, normandy, france.
The tone is emotional.